Mary Chrystie Papers, 1833-1841: Finding Aid
Cotsen Children's Library
Mary Chrystie Papers
1833-1841
1830s-1840s
COTSEN1
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Cotsen Children's Library One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
1.0 linear feet 1 Hollinger, 1 half-size archival box, 1 volume
Chrystie, Mary A., 1825-1842
A collection of letters and other writings written principally by Mary Chrystie, but also other members of Chrystie/Few family, mostly from the 1830s through 1840s. Mary Chrystie is a pious, intelligent, chatty, and wealthy young lady from Fishkill Landing, New York. Unfortunately Mary dies at the early age of 17 from tuberculosis in Nice, France.
Mary Chrystie is a pious, intelligent, chatty, and wealthy young lady from Fishkill Landing, New York. Unfortunately she is also sickly. She dies at the early age of 17 from tuberculosis in Nice, France, where her mother and father took her in order to spend the winter in a warm climate.
A collection of letters and other writings written principally by Mary Chrystie but also other members of her family. The collection mostly consists of correspondence between Mary Chrystie and her family members from 1833-1841, and Mary Chrystie's diary 1837-1841. Chrystie is a precocious, well-to-do child growing up in New York State and Princeton in the years leading up to the American Civil War.
Box 1: Letters, organized by correspondent. Box 2: Storybooks and Journals. Volume 3: Diary of Mary Chrystie.
This collection is open for research.
Gift of Bruce C. Willsie, class of 1986, in 2002.
No materials were separated during 2014 processing.
For additional biographical and geneological information about the Chrystie/ Few families and Mary Chrystie, as well as classroom teaching materials related to the collection, see notes by Eric Johnson at Seeley Mudd Manuscript Library.
Mary Chrystie Collection; 1856-2003; Princeton University Library Records, Princeton University Archives, Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, Princeton University Library.
Eric Johnson, Ohio State University, "Making Mary: Maternal Shaping and the Construction of Childhood in the Mary Christie Archive".
American poetry -- 19th century.; Boarding school students -- United States -- 19th Century; Homebound instruction -- United States -- 19th Century; Travelers, American -- 19th Century -- Diaries; Young adults -- United States -- 19th Century; American diaries -- 19th century.; American history/Civil War and Reconstruction; American history/Early national
- Correspondence, 1833-1841; 1830s-1840s; 15.0 folders (Box 1)
  Arranged mostly by individual correspondents, except where indicated as seperately collected material
  Correspondence mostly between Mary Chrystie and her close family members and friends from 1833-1841.
  - Letters to Frances Chrystie, 1830s; 21.0 items
    No discernible arrangement
    Mary's letters to her mother Frances Chrystie, spanning 1832-1837?, most letters undated, covering these topics of interest: sketches, poems, daily life, homesickness, Pelham Priory education, prayers, hymns, anniversary card.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1837-1840 September 2; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 39.5 cm Pages 3 and 4 are written with crossed, overlapping text. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Pelham Priory; postmarked September 3 (no year), New Rochelle, NY. Mary describes at length how she is caught in the middle of a convoluted spat between two of her friends and relates how her friends all call her "a perfect goose because I cannot think wrong of any one". Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Frances Chrystie, 1833 February 19; 4.0 pages 32 x 39 cm Includes pencil sketches. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At Fishkill Landing. Mary copies a number of texts from her textbooks and books belonging to her brother, with pencil sketches of insects, a bird, and plants.
    - To Frances Chrystie, 1833 February 19; 4.0 pages 19.4 x 31.8 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Five poems, at least one of which Mary copied.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 1.0 pages 10 x 19.6 cm On a fragment of paper. Includes pencil sketch. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Mary laments that she and her mother must suffer from headaches, but resolves to bear up under them as "God has sent them", with pencil sketch of a house at bottom. On verso is a hand written receipt: "Recd of A. Chrystie Eighteen dollars in full. Fishkill Landing, 9 March 1833, Robert Gilmer,".
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 1.0 pages 16.1 x 19.4 cm Includes pencil sketch. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A four line poem written by Mary addressed to her mother: "This is for my mother dear only i am a fraid she will not like it", with pencil sketch of a seaside scene.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 8 x 19.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      An original(?) poem.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 19.6 x 24.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Frances Chrystie, 1835; 2.0 pages 24.4 x 19.6 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Mary describes a pleasant day at play with her brother; with note in mother's hand: "At 10 years of age".
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1837-1840 July 16; 3.0 pages 24.8 x 38.8 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Pelem (sic) Priory; postmarked July 18 (no year), New York. Mary describes her lessons in French and archery and requests that she be sent supplies such as towels, a wash rag, a "deep green silk cape for most all the girls have them," and other materials. Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 9.7 x 20.1 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A "Sunday letter" Mary writes to her parents in which she turns a hymn into prose.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 7.5 x 14.9 cm Includes a sketch. One page folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A short note in which Mary expresses that she thinks that her friend Kitty is "a good girl and minds her work", with a pencil sketch of a house.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1837-1840 July 17; 4.0 pages 24.8 x 38.9 cm One sheet of paper folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      July 17 (no year), Pelham Priory, New York. Mary explains to her mother in detail her experience of homesickness. Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Frances Chrystie, 1833 February 18; 2.0 pages 6.7 x 9.7 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A short prayer which Mary addresses to her mother, with notation by Frances Chrystie at bottom of verso: "Written by dear M__ while I was at lunch".
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 2.0 pages 16.3 x 19.6 cm Scribbles in ink. Sketches on verso. One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A short note in which Mary apologizes for a fit of temper, with scribbles in ink and sketches on verso of outdoor scenes.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 9 x 19.5 cm Torn and missing a large chunk of text. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A short note in which Mary transcribes sentences from one of her textbooks ("union spelling and reading book").
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1836-1837 December 25; 4.0 pages 15.6 x 19 cm Torn and missing a large chunk of text. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      December 25 (no year), Princeton, New Jersey. In Frances Chrystie's(?) hand, statement that Mary was "About eleven years of age" when she wrote the letter, hence 1836-1837. Mary writes a letter to please her mother and includes in it a riddle of her own devising, also transcribes a hymn she has memorized.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 13.5 x 20.8 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A very affectionate letter to her mother in which Mary expresses her desire to please her parents.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1836-1837; 4.0 pages 19.5 x 24.5 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      No date, Princeton, New Jersey. In Frances Chrystie's(?) hand, statement that Mary was "About eleven years of age" when she wrote the letter, hence 1836-1837. Mary transcribes a hymn for her mother.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1832-1833; 4.0 pages 12 x 18.5 cm Includes pencil sketch. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      No date, but in Frances Chrystie's(?) hand, statement that Mary was "about 7 years of age" when she wrote the letter, hence 1832-1833. A short note to her mother with an original(?) poem entitled "The Beloved Sister", with pencil sketch of a flower.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 1.0 pages 15.9 x 19 cm Includes pencil sketches. One sheet with cut-out heart designs. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Adressed to "Mrs. Chrystie", 5 poems, with numerous sketches.
    - To Frances Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 12.5 x 19.5 cm Includes pen sketch. Letter had been folded into triangular shape. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      A card from Mary celebrating her parents' wedding anniversary, with pen sketch of two birds over a heart.
  - Letters to Albert Chrystie, 1840s; 5.0 items
    No discernible arrangement.
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her father Albert Chrystie, spanning 1841-1842, most letters undated. Includes 1 letter from J. W. Chrystie (Albert Chrystie's brother) to Albert Chrystie and two letters from Frances Chrystie (Mary Chrystie's mother) to Albert Chrystie. The letters cover these topics of interest: Arrival of Mary and Frances at Ms. Garrettson's in Rhinebeck, New York, description of the "country" in Rhinebeck, a funeral sermon, animals, Frances's illness, Mary thanks her father for a prayer book, a hymn, a eulogistic letter after Mary's passing.
    - To Albert Chrystie, 1841 June 10; 4.0 pages 25.7 x 40.9 cm Two letters on one sheet. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      June 10, 1841, Rhinebeck, New York; postmarked June 10 at Rhinebeck New York; two letters on one sheet (one by Mary and one by her mother, Frances). Mary writes to her father about her arrival, with her mother, at the house of Ms. Garrettson in the country. Frances writes to her husband describing how she and Mary have given themselves "up to the [natural] delights" surrounding them.
    - To Albert Chrystie, circa 1841 July 26; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 40.4 cm Three letters on one sheet. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      No date, postmarked July 26 (no year), New York, written while in the country at Rhinebeck; three letters on one sheet (two by Mary and one by her mother, Frances). In the first letter Mary mentions that her mother is ill, that she has been to a funeral sermon, and that her "bile has worked itself off by emiting a great quantity of blood;". In her second letter Mary again mentions her mother's illness and decribes her friendly encounters with local animals. In the third letter Frances describes her illness, "a little cold" caused "by the great change in weather". Year supplied by date of preceding letter (see series "Letters to Albert Chrystie", letter 1).
    - To Albert Chrystie, circa 1837-1840 September 12; 4.0 pages 25 x 40.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      No date, Pelham Priory, postmarked September 12 (no year), New Rochelle, New York. Mary thanks her father for a "very acceptable" prayer book which he has sent her and expresses her joy at not having to borrow one anymore. Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Albert Chrystie, Undated; 2.0 pages 12.3 x 18 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      No date; Mary transcribes a hymn for her father and expresses the wish that he will be pleased with her writing. She confidently states:"I think that it is very good".
    - To Albert Chrystie, 1842 December; 4.0 pages 25 x 40.3 cm; addressed cover sheet: 20 x 25 cm. One sheet; includes addressed cover sheet. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      December 1842, New York; from Albert Chrystie's brother J. W. Chrystie. A long eulogistic letter about Mary Chrystie (Albert Chystie's daughter), written as "a tribute of affection to a Brother dearly beloved, and to the memory of his daughter.. .". J. W. Chrystie was Mary's teacher for 3 years. Included with the letter is an addressed cover sheet with the following pencil-written note on verso: "Dear Brother, if you think it of sufficient importance I will write one a fairer copy of the enclosed. Mr J. C."
  - Letters to William Chrystie, 1835; 2.0 items
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her brother William Chrystie, one undated letter and one letter dated 1835. Includes 1 letter by Frances Chrystie. The letters cover these topics of interest: family activities, William's being away at school, daily life, and gratitude.
    - To William Chrystie, October 7, no year; 4.0 pages 24.9 x 39.9 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      October 7 (no year, but apparently written at a fairly young age), New York. Mary writes to her brother to tell him of family plans and doings while he is away at school; she closes with instructions to "direct your thoughts to God", for their mother and father are uneasy about his studies.
    - To William Chrystie, 1835 December 26; 4.0 pages 24.4 x 39.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      December 26, 1835, Princeton, New Jersey; postmarked December 29 at Princeton. 2 letters on one sheet (the first letter by Mary, the second letter by her Mother, Frances). Mary regales her brother with a description of her daily life and apologizes for not getting him a Christmas gift because "Princeton is a poor place and mama is loath to part with her money". Frances entreats Willie to send them more letters and reminds him to show his appreciation of a Mr. Dardan's generosity (he gave Willie a copy of Robinson Crusoe).
  - Correspondence With Catherine Few, 1837-1841; 6.0 items
    Letters written by Mary Chrystie come before letter written by other persons.
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her grandmother Catherine Few: one letter dated 1841, all other letters undated. Includes 3 letters from Mary's mother, Frances Chrystie, to her mother Catherine Few, 1 letter to Mary from Catherine, 1 letter to Frances from Catherine, and 1 letter from Mary Chrystie's aunt, Mary Few, to her mother, Catherine Few. The letters cover these topics of interest: Mary's playing, Mary's health, weather, Philadelphia, Josephus, Mary and a friend are frightened by a man following them, a courtroom scene, Mary's seeing various newspapers, and 3 paper cut-outs.
    - To Catherine Few, March 30, no year; 2.0 pages 19.58 x 24.2 cm One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      March 30 (no year), Fishkill Landing; 2 letters on 1 sheet (the first letter by Mary and the second leter by her mother, Frances). Mary thanks her grandmother Catherine for an earlier letter and relates how she spends her time at play. Frances tells Catherine (her mother) about Mary's (her daughter) health condition and the dissappointing weather.
    - To Catherine Few, January 30, no year; 4.0 pages 24.8 x 39.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      30 January (no year), Philadelphia; 2 letters (1 from Mary and 1 from Frances). Mary expresses satisfaction with her stay in Philadelphia, mentions that she is reading Josephus, and request a number of things including a visit from Catherine. Frances writes a touching note to her mother Catherine, concluding "... I can say most truly that your happiness is as dear to me as my own.. .".
    - To Catherine Few, March 6, no year; 3.0 pages 24.1 x 32.8 cm. 3 cut-outs of varying size. One sheet. 3 separate paper cut-outs sleeved together. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      March 6 (no year); postmarked March 6, Philadelphia. 2 letters (1 from Mary and 1 from Frances). Mary includes more news from Philadelphia including a frightening incident in which Mary and a friend are followed by a strange man, a description of a court scene, and the newspapers from various states in the court's reading room. Mary includes 3 paper cut-outs that reveal the figure of Shakespeare, Little Red Rding Hood, and an old lady. Frances writes a short note and complains of headaches.
    - To Catherine Few, circa 1837-1840 August 8; 4.0 pages 24.8 x 38.5 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      August 8 (no year), Pelham Priory; postmarked August 10 at New Rochelle, New York. A newsy letter from school in which Mary remarks that she is doing very well in her French and music lessons, expresses feelings of homesickness, sends her regards to the rest of the family, and challenges her mother to find "any words spelt wrong". Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Mary and Frances Chrystie, 1841 July 14; 4.0 pages 25.1 x 39.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      July 14, 1841, New York; postmarked July 15, New York. 2 letters (1 to Mary from Catherine and 1 to Frances from Catherine). In a very newsy letter to Mary, Catherine (Mary's grandmother) expresses her concern for Mary's health and commends her to God's care. In the letter to Frances, Catherine (Frances's Mother) offers to give Frances money to pay for the transportation of Mary to Virginia Springs in an effort to ease Mary's illness.
    - To Catherine Few, June 28, no year; 4.0 pages 24.2 x 38.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      No date; postmarked June 28 (no year) at New York. A letter from Mary Chrystie's aunt, Mary Few, to Catherine Few (Mary Few's mother). A newsy missive full of general information about a dinner party she hosted and the otherwise uneventful two days that have passed since Catherine departed for Brooklyn.
  - Letters to Maria Montgomery, 1830s-1840s; 6.0 items
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her maternal great aunt, Maria Montgomery. Spanning at least 1836-1840, most letters undated. Includes 2 letters from Frances Chrystie to Maria Montgomery. The letters cover these topics of interest: outdoor activities at Lebanonville including horseback riding, staying in the country, Mary's health and various illnesses, a thank-you note, a jump-rope game, swimming dogs, homesickness, Mary's complaints about her Madame, and knitting.
    - To Maria Montgomery, circa 1841 July 25; 4.0 pages 25.2 x 39.4 cm Mary Chrystie's green wax seal is attached to the letter. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      July 25 (no year), Lebanonville; 2 letters (1 from Mary and 1 from her mother, Frances). Mary Chrystie writes to her maternal great aunt, Maria Montgomery, about her outdoor activities at Lebanonville, including a session of horseback riding that made her "not the least afraid", but nevertheless left her sore: "... my bones acked (sic) so badly, at first I thought it was the rheumatism". Frances tells her Aunt, Maria Montgomery, about the pleasant time she and the family are having in the country, expresses concern over Mary's heatlh, and laments that the mail in Lebanonville is not "well regulated". Mary Chrystie's green wax "Mary" seal is attached. Year supplied by inference, the only year provided from Mary's time in Lebanonville is a letter to Anne Cambreleng, July 6, 1841 (see series 11 "Separately Collected Miscellaneous Letters", letter 11).
    - To Maria Montgomery, Undated; 1.0 pages 19.9 x 32.9 cm Content written on just a single section of one folded sheet. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Undated, apparently written when Mary was very young. A short thank-you note for the gift of a chair; the letter was written on an addressed cover sheet used earlier for a letter sent to Albert Chrystie.
    - To Maria Montgomery, circa 1840 July 24; 4.0 pages 24.7 x 39 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      July 24 (no year; 1840?), Pelham Priory; postmarked July 24 at New Rochelle; New York. Mary tells Maria, her maternal great aunt, about the fun she is having while not at her lessons: she describes a pair of swimming dogs and the near death of one of them and she explains how to play a jump-rope game called "fox and geese". Mary expresses homesickness and asks for supplies such as towels, a wash rag, a box of wafers, and a bottle of comphire.
    - To Maria Montgomery, circa 1840 August 17; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 39.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      August 17 (no year, but circa 1840), Pelham Priory; postmarked August 18 at New Rochelle, New York. A very busy letter in which Mary complains about Madame, explains in detail her attempt to make her mother a muslin collar, describes how a Mr. Lorillard, the owner of a snuff factory, has determined that Mary will be an old maid because she did not sneeze while taking a pinch of snuff, mentions that she has been "poisened (sic) pretty badly" but is coping with the help of flaxseed tea, states that she has lost the brooch her brother gave her, and notes that she is "distressingly in want of funds... nothing less than dollars will do.. .". Dates supplied are from descriptions of the same poisoning incident in "Separately Collected Miscellaneous Letters," items 1, 2, and 10.
    - To Maria Montgomery, circa 1840 September 26; 4.0 pages 25 x 40.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      September 26 (no year; but probably 1840 based on a date provided in the letter itself), Pelham Priory. A short letter in which Mary mentions that she has been suffering from a cough and sore throat, complains that two of her friends have not written her, and excitedly relates how she has marked the days until she is able to give "little Mary Wilkes" a white worsted cap that she will knit in the future on "the 14th of October 1840". (The sequence of marked days and further reference to this date are found on the rear pastedown of Mary's journal: "How I will jump when I can say this day is Wednesday 14 October 1840".)
    - To Maria Montgomery, 1836 January 15; 4.0 pages 24.9 x 39.5 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      January 15, 1836; postmarked January 16 at Princeton. 2 letters (1 from Mary and 1 from her mother, Frances). Various news from Mary, including an account of how she is now "working for poor children" by knitting and making caps. Frances describes Mary's recent bouts with stomach flu, fever, and respiratory problems; she also unfavorably compares Princeton to New York, saying of Princeton that it is "a bad place to bring up children".
  - Letters to Mary Few, circa 1832-1833; 2.0 items
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her aunt Mary Few (Frances Chrystie's sister). One letter with no year and one letter dated (post mortem) circa 1832-1833. Includes one letter from Mary's mother, Frances. The letters cover these topics of interest: flower arranging, Philadelphia, Mary's health, William's garden preperations, a pencil sketch of a farm, and a copied poem.
    - To Mary Few, May 1, no year; 4.0 pages 24.6 x 39.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      May 1 (no year), Philadelphia; postmarked May 4 at Philadelphia. One letter from Mary and one letter from Frances. Mary describes her time in Philadelphia arranging flowers and spending time with a girl named Mary Ingraham. Frances sends a newsy letter that briefly mentions Mary's state of health, but is otherwise full of details of the time she's spent in Philadelphia.
    - To Mary Few, circa 1832-1833; 1.0 pages 17.2 x 19.6 cm Includes pencil sketch. One sheet of ruled paper. (Box 1, Folder 6)